(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.2",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
今宵はきっと
Tonight is surely
雨が降る
going to rain.
6月
June
梅雨
Rainy Season (Tsuyu)
雨
Rain
猫又おかゆ
Nekomata Okayu
猫又おかゆ 梅雨ライブ
Nekomata Okayu Rainy Season Live
開催決定
Event Confirmed
【Okayu Ch. 猫又おかゆ】
【Okayu Ch. Nekomata Okayu】
6月19日21時 開演
June 19th at 21:00 Start
メーベル
Mabel
作詞/作曲：バルーン
Lyrics/Composition: Balloon
笑えないわ
I can't even laugh
「不幸になった」ってどの口が言うのだろう
Which mouth would say, "I've become unhappy"?
もう何回 誤魔化している その指で遊んでる
How many times have I glossed over it, playing with those fingers?
ふざけないで 被害者ぶったって 何も変わりはしないのに
Don't mess around, even if you play the victim, nothing will change.
こうやって 夜は更けてく おやすみ
And so, the night deepens. Good night.
だから 相対になるのは夜が明けてから
So, being opposites only happens after dawn.
ほらね 今日は眠るのさ
See? I'm going to sleep today.
そして こんな言葉に意味などはないから
And since these words have no meaning,
気にしないで 目を閉じて
Don't mind them, just close your eyes.
傷が付いて 変わっていった程度のものと言うのでしょう
You'd say it's just something that got scarred and changed.
もう何回 繰り返している その胸で眠ってる
How many times have I repeated this, sleeping on that chest?
不意に吐いた「嫌いじゃないよ」って その言葉で揺れるのに
Even though those words, "I don't hate you," breathed out suddenly, shake me,
そうやって 目を伏せるのは 何故 何故 何故
Why, why, why do you cast your eyes down like that?
曖昧になるのは嘘に怯えるから
Becoming ambiguous because I'm afraid of lies.
またね 遠く灯が揺れる
See you later, a light flickers in the distance.
ここで 愛情を問うにはあまりに遅いから
It's far too late to question affection here,
聞かなかったことにしよう
So let's act like I didn't hear it.
あー あー 青になって熟れる様な
Ah, ah, like ripening into blue...
あー あー 赤になって枯れる様な
Ah, ah, like withering into red...
拙い拙い想いだけ 募ってしまって仕方がないんだよ
Only these clumsy, clumsy feelings keep piling up, and I can't help it.
だから
So...
だから 相対になるのは夜が明けてから
So, being opposites only happens after dawn.
ほらね 今日は眠るのさ
See? I'm going to sleep today.
そして あんな言葉も優しさというから
And since you call those words kindness too,
触れる様な虚しさが残る
A hollowness that feels almost tangible remains.
残る
Remains...
フラジール
Fragile
作詞/作曲：ぬゆり
Lyrics/Composition: Nuyuri
くしゃくしゃになった診察券を持って
Holding a crumpled-up medical card,
簡単な想像に日々を使っている
I spend my days in simple imaginings.
単調な風景にふと眠くなって
Suddenly getting sleepy in the monotonous scenery,
回送列車に揺られ動いている
I'm moving, swayed by an out-of-service train.
看板の照明が後ろめたくなって 目を落とした先で笑っていた
Feeling guilty about the sign's illumination, I was laughing where I looked down.
The billboard lights grew shameful, and I saw someone laughing where I looked down
通りを抜けて 路地裏の方で 屈託もなく笑っていた
Passing through the street, in the back alley, they were laughing without a care
映画の上映はとうに終わっている
The movie screening has long since ended
叱責の記憶がやけに響くから
Because the memories of being scolded echo so loudly
できれば遠くに行かないでくれ
If possible, please don't go far away
出来るなら痛くしないで
If you can, please don't make it hurt
構わないで 離れていて 軋轢にきゅっと目をつむって
Don't mind me, stay away, closing my eyes tightly against the friction
報わないで 話をして 窓越しにじっと目を合わせて
Don't reward me, just talk to me, staring through the window, meeting your eyes
退廃に暮れた劇場の隅で
In the corner of a theater lost to decadence
眠らなかったはずが眠っている
I wasn't supposed to sleep, but I'm sleeping now
アラベスクには触れなかったんだ
I couldn't reach the Arabesque
火がついたように街が光った
The city lit up as if set on fire
無頓着なあの子が傘を差したら
When that indifferent girl opened her umbrella
それで救われるくらい単純でしょ
It's simple enough to be saved by just that, right?
左手の指輪 右手に隠して 戸惑ってるふうにしてた
Hiding the ring on my left hand with my right, acting as if I'm confused
捜さないで いつの間にか
Don't come looking for me, before I knew it
消えたことに気づく距離ならば
If we're at a distance where you'd notice I'm gone
許さないで 最初だけは
Don't forgive me, at least at first
悲しくもないはずにしたくて
I wanted to make it so it wouldn't even be sad
構わないで 離れていて 軋轢にきゅっと目をつむって
Don't mind me, stay away, closing my eyes tightly against the friction
報わないで 話をして 窓越しにじっと目を合わせて
Don't reward me, just talk to me, staring through the window, meeting your eyes
眠らないで 言葉にして
Don't fall asleep, put it into words
照らした光に目を細めて
Squinting in the light that shone on us
笑わないで 君に咲いた執着よ
Don't laugh, oh obsession that bloomed in you
僕を飲み込んでくれ
Please, swallow me whole
みんなー！
Everyone!
やっほー！
Yahoo!
僕が言った通り、今日雨降ったでしょ？
Just as I said, it rained today, didn't it?
今日はね、この傘とか、みんなちょっと気づいてると思うけど
Today, well, with this umbrella, and I think you've noticed,
この足元にある長靴。
these rain boots at my feet.
これすごいでしょ？
Aren't they great?
これは今日雨が降るだろうからって長靴を用意してもらったんだよ。
I had these rain boots prepared because it would likely rain today.
これ凄くない？ちゃんとほら、猫のさ、
Aren't these amazing? Look, there's like a cat...
このバッジみたいなのに白いリボンが付いてて
...badge thingy with a white ribbon on it,
で、なんかこう可愛い紫色への長靴になってるんだよ。
and it's a cute purple color.
元々ね、黄色い靴を履いてたから
I was originally wearing yellow shoes, so...
なんか凄いでしょ？
Doesn't it look great?
全体、全体の紫感がね凄い増えてて可愛いんだよ。
The overall purple vibe has increased a lot, it's cute.
で、この傘もね、これすごいでしょ？開けたり閉めたりできるんだよ。
And this umbrella too, isn't it amazing? You can open and close it.
オープン！ほらー！
Open! See!
ほら傘すごい、このね、お水でね、濡れてるんだよ傘も。
Look, the umbrella is amazing, it's wet with water, even the umbrella.
すごいよね。
Isn't it incredible?
みんなとね、相合傘しようと思えばね、できるんだよ。
If I feel like sharing an umbrella with everyone, I can.
ほら、こうかな？こっちの方にほら、みんなも入れるし。
Look, like this? Over here, see, everyone can fit in.
まぁちょっとこうすると、こう、仔犬。雨に濡れている...
Well, if I do this, it's like... a puppy. Drenched in rain...
…子犬を守る僕みたいな演出をね、感じることができます。
...you can feel the staging, like me protecting a puppy.
いや、でも今日はね、あのこれからまだまだたくさん、
But today, you know, from now on, even more...
雨がね、止みそうにないので、
the rain doesn't seem like it's going to stop, so...
その雨が止まない今夜は、僕の歌をたくさん聴いてもらえればいいなと思っています。
tonight while the rain won't stop, I hope you can listen to many of my songs.
では、次の曲行きたいと思います！
Now, let's go to the next song!
あー、あ、はい。
Ah, ah, yes.
なんかね、運営さんミスっちゃったんだって。
It seems like the staff made a mistake.
えー、次は屋上みたいなんっで、えー移動するからちょっと待っててね。
Um, next is like the rooftop, so wait a bit while I move.
次の曲、聴いてください。
Please listen to the next song.
プロトディスコ。
Proto Disco.
プロトディスコ / 作詞/作曲：ぬゆり
Proto Disco / Lyrics/Composition: nulut
同じだけ夢を見てる狡猾さに
In the cunning that sees the same dream
違う言葉を今ただ待ち続けている
Now just continuing to wait for different words
今しがた終わるはずだった想像に
In the imagination that was supposed to end just now
延命処置を続けてまだ息を注ぐ
Continuing life-sustaining treatment and still pouring in breath
代わりの利く感動を焼き増しのドラマチックをあなたへ
To you, replaceable emotions and reprinted drama
語り得ぬさいはての奥を無理矢理繋ぎ
Forcing a connection to the depths of the unspeakable end
奪わないで 無くさないで それから
Don't take it away, don't lose it, and then
どうかもっともっと嫌って際限なんか奪って
Please, hate me more and more, take away any limits
衝動なんかもうどうなってもいい
I don't care what happens to my impulses anymore
崇める意味が溢れる前に オリジナルの地獄に落ちて
Before the meaning of worship overflows, fall into your original hell
どうかもっともっと祈って這い蹲って祈って
Please, pray more and more, grovel and pray
偶像なんか追い縋っていて
Clinging to idols
失っている 零落している
Losing, falling into ruin
作り上げた虚無に胡座をかいていろ
Keep sitting cross-legged in the void you created
カラカラの脳味噌を絞り続けている
Continuing to squeeze my dried-up brain
踊らされることをまだ自覚している
Still aware of being danced around
安全な街の中で君が見据えているものは あたしだ あたしだ
In the safe city, what you're staring at is me, it's me
吐き出し捨てていくことさえ 咎められなくて
I can't even be blamed for spitting things out and throwing them away
笑わないで 厭わないで 歪んで
Don't laugh, don't mind, distort
どうかもっともっと惑ってキャッチーを奪って
Please, be more and more confused, take away the catchy
救援なんかもう来なくてもいい
Rescue doesn't have to come anymore
忘れるなんて出来ないくらい脳髄にちゃんと擦り込んで
Rub it into your brain so much that you can't forget
どうかもっともっと描いて空想なんて拭って
Please, draw more and more, wipe away those fantasies
盲信ばっかもう窮屈なの
Blind faith is just so cramped now
油を差して火を灯して 錆びついている言語に血を通してみて
Oil it, light a fire, and let blood flow through the rusted language
明快な回答は無く
There is no clear answer
こんな歌だって陳腐なんだ
Even a song like this is cliché
再来の審議ばっかで
Just deliberations on its return
まだ踊り足りないの！
I haven't danced enough yet!
どうかもっともっと嫌って際限なんか奪って
Please, hate me more and more, take away any limits
衝動なんかもうどうなってもいい
I don't care what happens to my impulses anymore
崇める意味が溢れる前に オリジナルの地獄に落ちて
Before the meaning of worship overflows, fall into an original hell.
どうか もっともっと描いて 後悔なんてしないで
Please, keep drawing more and more, and don't regret anything.
雑音なんて消えてしまえ
Let all the noise just vanish.
浪費している言葉で呼んで
Call out with the words you're wasting.
終わりのない温度で焼き尽くして 震わせてみてよ
Burn it all down with an endless temperature, and make me tremble.
はい、ということでプロトディスコでした！
Alright, and that was "Proto Disco"!
えー、一番最初メーベルから始まって、えー、フラジール、そしてプロトディスコまで来たんですけど、
Um, starting with "Mabel" at the very beginning, then "Fragile," and now we've come to "Proto Disco."
ま、ここまでは、ま、ちょっとロックな感じだけど少し、ま、しっとりというか、しっとりかっこいい感じの曲で、えー終わったんですけど、
So far, they've been a bit rock-inspired, but also somewhat mellow—or rather, mellow and cool. That's how we've wrapped up this part.
次の曲は、ま、この、ま結構ね激しく雨降ってるので、激しい感じの曲にも挑戦していこうかなと思ってます。
For the next song, since it's raining quite heavily here, I thought I'd challenge myself with a more intense song.
おーい！
Hey!
みんな、どこにいるんだろう？
I wonder where everyone is?
あっちかな？あっちかな？
Over there? Or maybe over there?
これからもね、ちょっとかっこいい僕をみんなに見せていければなと思うので、
I hope to keep showing everyone a cooler side of me from now on.
次の曲、いきたいと、思います！
So, I'd like to move on to the next song!
では、聞いてください。「アンドロメダアンドロメダ」。
Now, please listen to "Andromeda Andromeda."
アンドロメダアンドロメダ
作詞/作曲：ナユタン星人
Andromeda Andromeda
Lyrics/Composition: Nayutalien
ワレワレは宇宙人ダ 校舎の裏からコンタクト
"We are aliens." Contact from behind the school building.
プラズマはあなた狙う 届ける思いは超電波
Plasma is targeting you. The feelings I send are ultra-radio waves.
放課後の奇跡体験 感じているのギャラクシー
A miraculous after-school experience. I'm feeling the galaxy.
観測はあなた次第 渦巻く想いは恋心
Observation is up to you. These swirling feelings are love.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 答えておくれ
Andromeda Andromeda, please answer me.
あなたとわたし 永久に逢えないの
You and I can never meet for eternity.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 気づいておくれ
Andromeda Andromeda, please notice me.
彼方の宇宙であなたに恋してる
I'm in love with you in the far reaches of space.
パルラパルラパルラッタッタラ
Pal-la pal-la pal-lat-tat-ta-la
裏山で大放電 赤色光ったエレキテル
A massive discharge on the back hill. A glowing red "elekiter."
怪音がとおくで響く 夜中の3時に近所迷惑
A strange sound echoes in the distance. A nuisance to the neighbors at 3 AM.
屋上の秘密クラブ 感じてほしいのミステリー
A secret club on the rooftop. I want you to feel the mystery.
光線はあなた狙う 密かに撃ちぬくの恋心
The light beam is targeting you. Secretly piercing through my feelings of love.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 答えておくれ
Andromeda Andromeda, please answer me.
あなたとわたし 永久に逢えないの
You and I can never meet for eternity.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 忘れておくれ
Andromeda Andromeda, please forget me.
あなたと宇宙は本当によく似てる
You and the universe are truly very much alike.
パルラパルラパルラッタッタラ
Pal-la pal-la pal-lat-tat-ta-la
アンドロメダアンドロメダでした！
That was "Andromeda Andromeda"!
えっと、雨の音をずっと聴いてる時ってさ、どんな歌聴きたくなる？
Um, you know, when you've been listening to the sound of rain for a long time, what kind of songs do you feel like listening to?
僕は今回、雨の中でライブをするって決まったときには、
When I decided to do a live performance in the rain this time,
やっぱ雨が降ってるからちょっとこう、
クールな感じもいいなって思ってたんだけど、
since it's raining, I thought a cool vibe
would be nice, but...
でもやっぱ見てるみんなが少し、
胸の奥が熱くなるような曲を選びたいなって思ったので、
I also wanted to choose songs that would make
the viewers' hearts feel a bit warmer,
今回はちょっとクールだけど、
so this time, while they are a bit cool,
聴いてると少しなんか胸の奥が熱くなるような曲を
たくさん歌っていこうと思っています。
I'm planning to sing many songs that also
warm the heart when you listen to them.
おっ、じゃあそろそろ次の曲なんだけど、
Oh, well, it's almost time for the next song,
うーん。あっ、そうだ。歌のイメージに合わせて、
モード、変えてみよっか。
Hmm... Oh, I know! Let's try changing
the "mode" to match the image of the song.
うおー、いい感じに暗くない？
Whoa, isn't it nice and dark?
これにしよう。
Let's go with this.
（ラララ...）
(La la la...)
邪魔
作詞/作曲：syudou
Jama
Lyrics/Composition: syudou
今更何にも言わないが
お前の態度が気に食わぬ
I won't say anything now,
but I don't like your attitude.
気配り上手で聞き上手
他言無用もお手の物
Good at being attentive and a good listener.
Keeping secrets is your forte too.
おまけに突飛な輩にも
小馴れた手つきで擬態処理
And even with eccentric people,
you handle them with practiced ease.
聖人君子の生き字引
不平不満も漏らさずに
A living dictionary of virtue,
without even leaking a complaint.
誰彼皆々お前らの
味方になるけれど
Everyone will take your side, but...
それでもアタシは許さない
認めない
Still, I won't forgive you.
I won't accept you.
人目避けて行こうぜ
（ラララ...）
Let's go, avoiding the eyes of others.
(La la la...)
死のみぞ一斉送信
（ラララ...）
Simultaneous transmission of death only.
(La la la...)
嫉妬で駆けて行こうぜ
（ラララ...）
Let's run on jealousy.
(La la la...)
乳飲み子一転攻勢
（ラララ...）
A nursing child suddenly turns to offensive.
(La la la...)
アタシが善とは思わぬが
お前が善などヘドが出る
I don't think I'm good,
but the thought of you being good makes me sick.
とは言え現世の目は明らか
自問自答で夜は暮れる
Still, the eyes of the world are clear.
The night passes in self-questioning.
理屈や倫理や常套句
はたまた論拠さえ
Logic, ethics, clichés, or even grounds...
アタシの前では通じない
聞こえない
Don't work in front of me.
I can't hear them.
意味を殺してしまえよ
（ラララ...）
Just kill the meaning.
(La la la...)
好きに狂ってしまえよ
（ラララ...）
Just go crazy as you like.
(La la la...)
いつも呪って歌うよ
（ラララ...）
I'll always sing while cursing.
(La la la...)
頬を通って伝うよ
（ラララ...）
It travels down my cheeks.
(La la la...)
御託に酔っておられますが
さしずめあんたも個人主義
You're drunk on your own preachiness,
but ultimately, you're an individualist too.
敵無く生きてく事なんざ
所詮お前にゃ無理なのさ
Living without enemies is
impossible for you after all.
人目避けて行こうぜ
（ラララ...）
Let's go, avoiding the eyes of others.
(La la la...)
死のみぞ一斉送信
（ラララ...）
Simultaneous transmission of death only.
(La la la...)
嫉妬で駆けて行こうぜ
（ラララ...）
Let's run on jealousy.
(La la la...)
乳飲み子一転攻勢
（ラララ...）
A nursing child suddenly turns to offensive.
(La la la...)
ということで、邪魔、いかがだったでしょうか？
So, how did you like "Jama"?
やっぱちょっとね、こうダークでかっこいい感じの曲だから、
It's a dark and cool song,
まあこういうね、天気の日だからこそ
なんか歌いたいなっていう気持ちになったんだよね。
so I felt like singing it precisely
because of this kind of weather.
なんか天気が良くない日のほうが、
I feel more like listening to dark songs
そういうダークな曲聴きたいなっていう気持ちに
なるんだけど、みんなはどうかな？
on days when the weather isn't good.
How about everyone else?
あ、でも天気が悪いから逆に、なんだろうな、すごい元気が...
Ah, but because the weather is bad, conversely,
I wonder, maybe really energetic...
雨が降ってる時に、こういう屋上で聞きたいみたいなのも
When it's raining, I think people might want to hear
あるかもしれないよね。
songs like that on a rooftop.
ちなみに、この曲は...
By the way, this song...
すごいこの「邪魔」という曲はね、ダークな
this song 'Zama' is very dark
かっこいい感じだったから、
and cool, so
明るいステージとかで、こう歌ってもいいなと思ったんだけど、
I thought singing it on a bright stage would be good too,
やっぱ今日はこういうさ、こう屋上でさ、
but today, on a rooftop like this,
天気も悪くてさ、
with this bad weather,
こういう時にこそやっぱ「邪魔」を歌いたいっしょって
I thought 'Zama' is exactly what I want to sing
僕は思ったんだよね。
at a time like this.
あははは。
Ahahaha.
あ、何？何何何？
Oh, what? What, what, what?
あ、はは！
Ah, haha!
なんかさ、今さ、運営さんからさ、
Actually, I just got a message from management,
「おかゆさんなんか手の振りとかこういう、何ていうの？
'Okayu-san, your hand movements and, how should I say,
所作っつーのかな？所作みたいなのが
your gestures? Your gestures
なんか超良かったよ」って今褒められたんだけど。
were really great,' they complimented me.
あははは。
Ahahaha.
「なんか意識してることあるんですか？」って聞かれたけどさ、
They asked, 'Are you conscious of doing anything specific?'
別にないんですけど。
But I'm not really.
あはは！
Ahaha!
普段の、普段の美しさなんですけど。
It's just my usual, everyday beauty.
あははは！
Ahahaha!
やっぱ普段はね、2Dの時とかだとさ、手のなんかこういう動きとかはさ、
Usually, like in 2D, you can't really see
わかんないからさ、
these kinds of hand movements,
でも僕普段からこうやってなんか、こう麗しいんだよね、手の動きがね。
but even normally, my hand movements are elegant.
あはははは！
Ahahahahaha!
まあ、続き、まだまだね続きますんで、
Well, there's still more to come,
こういうなんか動きなんかにもね、注目してもらえればなと思います。
so I hope you'll pay attention to these movements too.
あはは。
Ahaha.
運営さん褒めてくれてありがとう。
Thank you for the compliment, management.
なんか意外なとこ褒められてびっくりなんですけど。
I'm surprised they praised such an unexpected thing.
さあちょっとね、なんか、いっぱい歌ってきて、ちょっと疲れたからさ、
Now then, I'm a bit tired from singing so much,
座るとこ探そうかな。
so I'll look for a place to sit.
おーー。
Ohh.
はあ〜、高いところってさ、
Ahh, high places,
なんかいいよね。
they're nice, aren't they?
看板とか、車の明かりがさ、
The signs and car lights,
雨でキラキラって光ってて、
they're sparkling in the rain,
見てて飽きないんだ。
and I never get tired of looking at them.
そうそう、高いところから、街を見下ろしてる感じの曲を
That's right, I remembered a song that feels like
思い出したんだ。
looking down at the city from a high place.
聞いてくれる？
Will you listen?
絶え間なく藍色
作詞/作曲：獅子志司
Taemanaku Aiiro
Lyrics/Composition: Shishi Shishi
エゴの満場　理性の冷凍
A crowded house of egos, a freezing of reason
あてのない最前線にどうして
Why am I at this aimless front line?
僕らは希望持って
We held onto hope,
恐れては叫んだ
shouting out our fears.
無知の彼は僕の頭上
His ignorance looms above me.
如何せんアイロニー　告げてタイトに
Unfortunately, it's irony, declared tightly.
栄誉なんて案外ノリ
Glory is unexpectedly just a whim.
変わってくランデブー　日々睨んでいく
A changing rendezvous, glaring at the days.
不甲斐ない夢はもう十分です
I've had enough of these worthless dreams.
大乱戦のオーダーメイド　やったもん勝ちに躊躇
A tailor-made battle royale, hesitating at the 'winner takes all' rule.
捨て去れ左脳も意地も
Throw away your logic and your pride.
類のない有頂天へと　突いて上がれ少年Aよ
To an unparalleled ecstasy, rise up, Boy A!
稀代の未来を掲げるくらいの
Enough to hold up a future of a lifetime.
盲点の発想　本末は転倒
A blind-spot idea, putting the cart before the horse.
正解のない矛盾の向こうに二乗
Squared beyond a contradiction with no answer.
僕らは持論持って
We held onto our own theories,
もがいては嘆いた
struggling and lamenting.
無垢な心情じゃ1の二乗
With an innocent heart, it's just one squared.
如何せんアイロニー　告げてタイトに
Unfortunately, it's irony, declared tightly.
不滅なんて安牌のみ
Immortality is only for the safe ones.
いざ行かん我がメロス　寝ずのエンドレス
Let's go, my Melos, an endless sleeplessness.
くだらない夢にまた踊っています
I'm dancing again to a worthless dream.
等身大の自己嫌悪　抱いて綴れ「こうでいたい」と
Embrace your life-sized self-loathing and write, 'I want to be like this.'
付属に富豪も飢えも
Accompanied by wealth and hunger.
酸いも甘いも中の下で　満足なんて宙の上で
The bitter and sweet are lower-middle, satisfaction is high in the air.
次の次も報われはしないの？
Won't I be rewarded even after the next time?
二兎追う者のみ
Only those who chase two rabbits,
目には手を
hand to the eye.
笑う門に来る事変よ
Oh, the incident that comes to the laughing gate!
向いていないと杭を打って
Driving a stake in, saying I'm not suited for this,
ついていないと賽を置いた
casting the dice, saying I'm unlucky.
向いてないと杭を打って ついてないと賽を置いた
I hammered a stake saying I wasn't suited, and cast the die saying I wasn't lucky
目覚めればまた藍色に
When I wake up, it's indigo again
絶え間ないが 届かないのは嫌なんだ
It's constant, but I hate not being able to reach
大乱戦のオーダーメイド やった者勝ちの名誉
A custom-made free-for-all, the honor belongs to the winner
踊れ 恐れを超えて
Dance, beyond the fear
悔いはないと心臓売った 勝算なんてない まだだ 僕は
I sold my heart, saying I have no regrets. There's no chance of winning. Not yet, I am...
如何せん隘路に告げて 対等に
Somehow, I'll tell the narrow path, and be equal
来世で会えたら 限りないこの浮世に笑おう
If we meet in the next life, let's laugh in this boundless fleeting world
銃を持って憂いを放て 時代を露わに
Take up a gun, release the sorrow, and expose the era
あ、このビルの下によさそうな場所発見！
Ah, I found a good-looking place under this building!
あそこで歌ったら超楽しそうじゃん。
It looks like it would be super fun to sing there.
おにぎりゃーのみんな、ちょっと移動してもいい？
Onigiri-ya, is it okay if we move a bit?
あ、いいんだね。
Ah, I see it's okay.
よし！じゃあOKみたいだから、移動するぞー！
Alright! Since it seems okay, let's move!
おおー、いいじゃんいいじゃん、この雰囲気。
Ooh, this is nice, this atmosphere.
とりあえず、今日はここまでたくさん歌ってきたけどさ、みんなどうだった？
Anyway, I've sung a lot so far today, but how was it for everyone?
僕はね、こんなに土砂降りの中で気持ちよく歌を歌える機会なんてあんまりないからさ。
For me, I don't often get the chance to sing so comfortably in such a downpour.
すごい貴重な機会だったし、めちゃめちゃ楽しかった。えへへ。
It was a very precious opportunity, and it was so much fun. Ehehe.
たまには外でね、思い切り歌を歌うのもいいなーって思ったよ。
I thought it was nice to sing my heart out outside once in a while.
僕引きこもりだからね、そんなにお外に行かないんだけどね。
I'm a shut-in, so I don't go outside that much.
こういう日も、まああってもいいかなって思ったし、少し雨が好きになったかな。
I thought a day like this might be okay too, and I think I've come to like the rain a little more.
今まではね、なんか雨って自分が外に出る機会があるあんまりなんか降ってると...
Until now, whenever it rained when I had to go outside...
...傘差すのめんどくさいし嫌だなって思ってたんだけどさ。
...I thought it was a pain to carry an umbrella and I hated it.
まあこういう日があってもいいなってちょっと、思えるきっかけになったかな。
Well, I think this became an opportunity for me to think that a day like this is fine.
あとはさ、この傘！傘すごいよねやっぱりさ。
And also, this umbrella! This umbrella is really amazing, after all.
このビニール傘と長靴、運営さんにね作ってもらったんだけどさ。
This vinyl umbrella and these boots were made for me by the staff.
何回見てもさ、凄くないこれ？
No matter how many times I look at it, isn't this amazing?
ほら見て見て。ほら濡れてんのいっぱい。
Look, look. See, it's all wet.
これからねこの運営さんにもらった傘を使って、いっぱい雨の日もお出かけしようって思ったよ。
I thought I'd use this umbrella I got from the staff to go out a lot on rainy days too.
ということで、ここまでいっぱい歌ったり喋ったりしてきましたけど。
So, I've been singing and talking a lot up to this point.
いよいよまもなく、フィナーレが近づいているということでね。
And now, the finale is finally approaching.
最後は二曲連続で歌わせていただこうと思います。
For the end, I'd like to sing two songs in a row.
よっと。
Up we go.
それでは聞いてください。バレリーコ。
Now, please listen. Balleriko.
バレリーコ
作詞/作曲:みきとP
Balleriko
Lyrics/Composition: MikitoP
純情少女と勘違いされて 全校男子に狙われた
Misunderstood as a pure girl, I was targeted by all the boys in school
あぁ初体験 世にも恐ろし大出血乗り越え 恥ずべきものはなし
Ah, my first time. Overcoming a terrifyingly large hemorrhage, there is nothing to be ashamed of
朱いりぼんヒラヒラさせて バイバイ プリマの放課後だ
Fluttering my scarlet ribbon, bye-bye, it's after school for the prima
あぁ青春さん 汗と涙でベタベタになってなんか大変そうですね
Ah, Mr. Youth, you're sticky with sweat and tears, you seem to be having a hard time
ゆらり揺れるジャンパースカート ひっそり覗くスラックス
A swaying jumper skirt, slacks quietly peeking out
目と目をあわせて戸惑うフリした 校内男女の関係
Making eye contact and pretending to be bewildered, the relationship between boys and girls in school
ねえ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding ding dang, let's dance
じょうずに飛び跳ねて エッサホイサ
Leaping skillfully, essa-hoisa
劣等感 ほら恥ずかしい それも人生だ
Inferiority complex, look, it's embarrassing. That's life too
ねえ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding ding dang, let's dance
もっともっと激しく エッサホイサ
More and more intensely, essa-hoisa
絶頂感 ほら最後まで面倒みてあげる
Euphoria, look, I'll take care of you until the end
うわばきでシャル・ウィ・ダンス
Shall we dance in our indoor shoes?
先輩どうしてあの子がんの　私の方がよい子でしょ
Senpai, why is that girl there? I'm a much better girl, right?
あぁ　奇々怪々　邪魔する猫はしっしっし　今すぐ踵を返しなさい
Ah, how strange. Shoo, shoo, to the meddling cat. Turn back on your heels right now.
ふわり香るリップクリーム　じっとり濡れたセミロング
A softly scented lip balm. Drenched semi-long hair.
教師の言葉もひぐらしの声も聞こえない男女の関係
A relationship where neither a teacher's words nor the cicadas' cries can be heard.
ねえ　ディン・ディン・ダン　さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding-ding-dan, let's dance.
じょうずに飛び跳ねて　エッサホイサ
Jump around skillfully, essa-hoisa.
劣等感　ほら恥ずかしい　それも人生だ
An inferiority complex, look, how embarrassing. That too is part of life.
ねえ　後悔はどこにあるの　九回転のピルエット
Hey, where is the regret? A nine-rotation pirouette.
トゥシューズぬいだ素足の　歪な叫び
The distorted scream of bare feet after taking off toe shoes.
「…もう限界だ」
"...It's my limit."
もう限界だ
It's my limit.
ねえ　先輩どうして泣いてるの？　一緒にアン・ドゥ・トロワして
Hey, Senpai, why are you crying? Let's do un, deux, trois together.
マスカレード？　どちらにするの？　オデット？　オディール？
Masquerade? Which one will it be? Odette? Odile?
ねえ　ディン・ディン・ダン　さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding-ding-dan, let's dance.
じょうずに飛び跳ねて　エッサホイサ
Jump around skillfully, essa-hoisa.
劣等感　ほら恥ずかしい　それも人生だ
An inferiority complex, look, how embarrassing. That too is part of life.
ねえ　グッバイ最後に踊りましょう
Hey, goodbye, let's dance one last time.
もっともっと激しく　エッサホイサ
More and more intensely, essa-hoisa.
絶頂感　今この瞬間　すべて完璧だ
A sense of climax, in this moment, everything is perfect.
うわばきでシャル・ウィ・ダンス
Shall we dance in our indoor shoes?
最後の曲、聴いてください。
Please listen to the final song.
ラストリゾート。
Last Resort.
くしゃくしゃの頭の中で考えている
Thinking inside my messy head.
十四時過ぎに開いた目がぼやけてる
My eyes, opened after 2 PM, are blurred.
嗚呼またやって来た今日に舌打ちをして始まる僕の最終演目
Ah, clicking my tongue at the day that's come again, my final performance begins.
四十二度溜息とスモーク　嗚呼リンス切れてたんだ
A 42-degree sigh and smoke. Ah, I ran out of conditioner.
四十二度洗濯も溜まってたんだ　まあもういっか
A 42-degree pile of laundry was also sitting there. Well, whatever.
狭くなったベランダの様だ　ゴミ溜めの様だ
It's like a narrowed balcony. Like a garbage dump.
それが僕だった
That was me.
さあ何処までだって行こうか　嗚呼此処までだって笑った
So let's go as far as we can. "Up to here," I laughed.
逃げ場の無い世界で逃避行　恐れは無いなもう無いな
A getaway in a world with no place to run. I have no fear, not anymore.
歩き疲れたところで終わりにしようか
Shall we end it where we've grown tired of walking?
愛しくて堪らないからって　飼い慣らし過ぎてぎゅっと
Because I love it so much, I've tamed it too much and held it tight.
手を繋いだままの怠惰が
The laziness of holding hands...
こっちを見て笑った　こんなもんさと何度も笑った
It looked at me and laughed. "This is how it is," it laughed again and again.
憐れむ様な遠い目で
With pitying, distant eyes.
さあ何処までだって行こうか　嗚呼此処までだって分かった
So let's go as far as we can. "Up to here," I understood.
行き場の無い世界に花束を　何でもいいよもういいよ
A bouquet for a world with no place to go. Anything's fine, it's enough already.
見渡す限り僕だけ置き去りみたいだ
As far as I can see, it seems I'm the only one left behind.
ラストリゾート
Last Resort
#おかゆの梅雨ライブ
#Okayu'sRainySeasonLive
嗚呼 散々だって嘆いた
Ah, I lamented that it was terrible
もう何回だって憂いた
I've grieved so many times already
宛名の無い助けは届かずに
The unaddressed help never arrived
何にも無い もう無いよ
There's nothing, nothing left anymore
殴り連ねた言葉と終わりに行こうか
Shall we go to the end with these scribbled words?
嗚呼 これでよかったんだって
Ah, saying that this was for the best
そう何度も唱えて
Chanting it over and over
掴めずに消えてゆくユートピア
A utopia that vanishes without being grasped
あの時きっとねえきっと
At that time, surely, hey, surely
引き返すには少しだけ遅すぎたようだ
It seems it was just a little too late to turn back
終わりを告げた
Announced the end
綺麗な日だった
It was a beautiful day
バイバイ
Bye-bye
梅雨ライブ
Rainy Season Live
今宵はきっと雨が降る
Surely it will rain tonight